If you’re anything like me,
you have lots of ambitious
plans for the future.
I’ve got a whole series of
new books I want to write,
thousands more
videos to script.
But guess what?
None of us may be able to do
any of the things we want to do
if we don't have our health.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Did you know that billions are spent
on glucosamine supplements every year?
Well, do they work?
Are they safe?
Let's find out.
Global sales
of glucosamine supplements
is estimated at $2 billion.
Glucosamine is a precursor
to two of the major components
of cartilage,
though at the marginal
blood levels
achieved by supplementation,
one would not expect it
to contribute much
to cartilage formation directly.
There are marked inconsistencies
in the clinical research
literature
as to whether it works at all.
The most potent predictor
of trial results?
Industry funding.
Studies sponsored
by the product makers themselves
showed that their patented
products were beneficial,
but independently-funded studies
showed glucosamine
had no effect.
This has raised
serious concerns
about "publication bias,"
the suspicion
that the glucosamine industry
quietly shelved rather than
published any studies
that didn't go their way
to give an overly rosy picture
in the medical literature.
This is what led in part
to the current American College
of Rheumatology guidelines
strongly recommending against
the use of glucosamine.
The proscription
against glucosamine
is echoed by some expert
consensus guidelines,
for example, the American
Academy of Orthopedic Surgeons
and Osteoarthritis
Research Society International,
but not others,
such as the European Society
for Clinical
and Economic Aspects
of Osteoporosis,
Osteoarthritis,
and Musculoskeletal Diseases,
which allows an exception
for pharmaceutical-grade
glucosamine.
Only this patented so-called
"crystalline" glucosamine
sold as a prescription-only drug
in Europe
has been decisively shown
to improve osteoarthritic
joint pain or function,
whereas the over-the-counter
glucosamine supplements
sold in the U.S.
offered mixed results
with no overall effect,
presumably because of
quality control analyses
by Consumer Reports and others
found glucosamine supplements
sometimes contained
no glucosamine at all.
An investigation of over
a dozen glucosamine supplements
found that only one contained
the claimed dose on the label.
So, maybe the inconsistency
in findings
is less a matter
of funding bias
and more a reflection
of the efficacy
of using genuine glucosamine.
I'd feel more confident
in the industry results
if they were more transparent
with their participant-level
results.
A request for data sharing was
reportedly denied by the owner
of the crystalline
glucosamine trials,
which "raises concerns
about the robustness
of their study findings."
Regardless, the effect size
of the pain relief
found even in the best studies
of crystalline glucosamine
can be considered
relatively small.
Effect size can be quantified
as a "standardized
mean difference."
An effect size of 0.2
is considered small,
0.5 moderate, and 0.8 large.
The effect size
of the best studies
on crystalline glucosamine,
0.27,
representing a small effect.
So, prescription glucosamine
works better than Tylenol,
but on par
with placebo injections
and less than NSAID drugs
like ibuprofen.
Now, glucosamine is safer
than NSAIDs,
but the tantalizing possibility
is that it could offer more
than just symptomatic relief.
Two industry-funded
randomized controlled trials
found that those
with knee osteoarthritis
randomized to take
the prescription glucosamine
for three years
experienced less progression
of their disease
compared to placebo,
as quantified
by X-ray measurements.
Those on the glucosamine
had a 62 percent reduction
in osteoarthritis progression
as measured
by joint space narrowing
compared to those randomized
instead to placebo.
However, two subsequent
non-industry-funded studies
found no benefit
on osteoarthritis disease
progression,
resulting in no benefit overall
when all four studies
were combined.
But how's this for a purported
potential side effect:
a longer life?
Glucosamine supplementation
extends the lifespan
of both microscopic worms
and aging mice.
What about people?
In 2012, the Vitamins
and Lifestyle cohort
was the first to report
on the relationship
between glucosamine use
and mortality.
About 75,000
Washington State residents
aged 50 through 76
were followed
for about seven years,
and those taking glucosamine
were 18 percent less likely
to die in that period.
In 2020,
two other cohort studies
were published on the matter,
including the enormous
UK Biobank study
that followed nearly
a half million people
for nine years.
Glucosamine users were
15 percent less likely to die,
and in a 2020
national U.S. study,
users had 27 percent lower risk
of death.
Since glucosamine use
has been associated
with lower CRP blood levels,
researchers suggested
this may be
an anti-inflammatory effect,
but when actually put
to the test,
glucosamine doesn't appear
to affect CRP at all.
A more likely explanation
may be the so-called
"healthy user effect."
Those who choose
to take supplements
tend to be healthier
than those who don't.
Studies show
dietary supplement users
are more likely to be female,
more educated,
and make healthier
diet and lifestyle choices,
such as exercising more
and smoking less,
and being less sick.
So, presumably, that's why
observational studies found
that those who take vitamins
may have lower mortality rates,
but when put to the test
in interventional studies,
there was no benefit or worse.
One of the most dramatic
examples
of the healthy user effect
is the finding that elders
who take flu vaccines
appear to cut their risk
of all-cause winter mortality
by 50 percent,
when seasonal flu itself
rarely causes
more than 10 percent
of excess winter deaths.
That's why randomized
controlled trials
are so critical to establishing
cause and effect,
and we have no such data
as of yet for glucosamine.
The cohort studies
did try to adjust
for factors such as age,
obesity, exercise education,
and smoking status,
but it's not possible to control
for unmeasured
lifestyle confounders.
In our next story,
we ask why some clinical guidelines
recommend chondroitin supplements
but others do not.
Chondroitin is a structural
component of cartilage
commonly used
as a dietary supplement
for osteoarthritis
that shares a similar story
with glucosamine.
There's a large heterogeneity
in outcomes,
with the industry-funded studies
showing a benefit
for symptomatic relief
and the non-industry-funded
studies showing no effect,
with a small effect size
similar to glucosamine.
Considering just the largest,
best-run studies,
the benefit of chondroitin
was found to be
"minimal or nonexistent"
and its use "therefore
be discouraged."
Like glucosamine,
the current American College
of Rheumatology guidelines
"strongly recommend against"
the use of as chondroitin
for knee or hip osteoarthritis,
along with the American Academy
of Orthopedic Surgeons
and Osteoarthritis Research
Society International,
whereas the European Society
for Clinical
and Economic Aspects
of Osteoporosis,
Osteoarthritis,
and Musculoskeletal Diseases
again allow
for the use
of pharmaceutical-grade,
prescription-only chondroitin.
Chondroitin is
typically extracted
from animal cartilage-
shark fins, bovine,
and chicken windpipes,
or pig noses-
and slaughterhouse
supply chains
are not known for their "good
manufacturing practices."
The lack of purity
and presence of contaminants
is blamed in part for the lack
of consistent reproducibility.
A study of 32 chondroitin
supplements on the market
found that only five
contained the labeled amount,
and some contained none.
Terms like "quality tested"
or retail price
were found to provide no basis
for judging quality.
Some of the cheapest
and the most expensive
chondroitin on the market
contained less than 10 percent
actual chondroitin.
When the National
Institutes of Health
set out to design
the esteemed GAIT trial,
the Glucosamine/Chondroitin
Arthritis Intervention Trial,
they ruled out
20 different commercial products
for issues like quality control
before giving up
and just deciding to have it
specially made themselves.
More than 1500 patients
with symptomatic
knee osteoarthritis
were randomized to take
standard daily doses
of glucosamine, chondroitin,
both glucosamine
and chondroitin,
an NSAID
anti-inflammatory drug,
or a placebo for six months.
Only the drug beat out placebo
for pain management.
Neither glucosamine
and chondroitin alone
or in combination
reduced pain effectively,
and neither did it have
any significant effect
on delaying disease progression
on X-ray.
Chondroitin also failed
in a two-year study,
but two other trials
found that by year two
objective benefits
could be found,
and a third using
more sensitive imaging (MRI)
could pick up
protective effects
by six months.
If you want to give it a try,
there's now
a purified non-animal source
of chondroitin
made from scratch
that should be free
of contaminants.
In the U.S., chondroitin
and glucosamine
are almost always sold
in a combination pill.
Like in the GAIT trial,
a meta-analysis of studies
pitting both
against osteoarthritis
found no clinically significant
benefit.
However, there had
never been a trial
in which pharmaceutical-grade,
prescription-only preparations
of both were used together
until finally
one was published in 2017.
The multicenter
randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled
clinical trial
had to be stopped prematurely
because one group was doing
so much better than the other
that it was deemed unethical
to continue.
But that superior treatment
was the placebo!
Unexpectedly,
when the code was broken,
it turned out that
the placebo group did better!
In other words,
the industry-funded study
found that their own
pharmaceutical-grade
chondroitin/glucosamine
was making the pain
significantly worse
compared to a sugar pill.
In the sugar pill group,
47 percent had
at least a 50 percent
improvement
in pain or function,
compared to just 28 percent
in the chondroitin/glucosamine
group.
What the chondroitin/glucosamine
users did get
was more side effects,
such as diarrhea
and abdominal pain;
so, doctors may want
to tell their patients
to stop taking their glucosamine
and chondroitin
as it is less effective
than placebo.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age” has
been out for about half a year now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.